<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
<!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<!-- When no,  put comments at end in comments section,
                                 otherwise,  put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<!-- When yes,  insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a
                                 string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the
                                 beginning of each paragraph of text. -->
<!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.
         Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents, but idnits insists on a ToC
         if the document has more than 15 pages. -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC -->
<!-- Choose the options for the references.
         Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer
         numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
         The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- If "yes",  causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
                                 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes" also. -->
<!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each
         main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items.
         If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
<rfc category="bcp"
     docName="draft-ietf-mtgvenue-iaoc-venue-selection-process-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">IAOC Plenary Meeting Venue Selection Process</title>

    <author fullname="Ray Pelletier" initials="R." surname="Pelletier">
      <organization>Internet Society</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>rpelletier@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Laura Nugent" initials="L." surname="Nugent">
      <organization>Association Management Solutions</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>lnugent@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." surname="Crocker">
      <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L." surname="Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Jacobsen" initials="O." surname="Jacobsen">
      <organization>The Internet Protocol Journal</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>olejacobsen@me.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jim Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin">
      <organization>INOC</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>jim@inoc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F." surname="Baker">
      <organization/>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>fred@cisco.com        </email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>IAOC</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This documents the IAOC's IETF Meeting Venue Selection Process from
      the perspective of its goals and thought processes. It points to
      additional process documents on the IAOC Web Site that go into further
      detail and are subject to change with experience.</t>
    </abstract>

    <!--
        <note title="Foreword">
        </note>
        -->

    <!--
      <texttable anchor="table_example" title="A Very Simple Table">
      <preamble>Tables use ttcol to define column headers and widths.
      Every cell then has a &quot;c&quot; element for its content.</preamble>
          <ttcol align="center">ttcol #1</ttcol>
                                    <ttcol align="center">ttcol #2</ttcol>
                      <c>c #1</c>        <c>c #2</c>
                      <c>c #3</c>        <c>c #4</c>
                      <c>c #5</c>        <c>c #6</c>
      <postamble>which is a very simple example.</postamble>
      </texttable>
    -->
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--
      <t>There are multiple list styles: "symbols",  "letters", "numbers",
"hanging",  "format", etc.</t>
      <t>
    <list style="symbols">
        <t>First bullet</t>
        <t>Second bullet</t>
    </list>
     </t>
-->

    <!--
<figure anchor="reference" title="Figure">
<artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[
    ASCII artwork goes here...
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
-->

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes the IETF Meeting Venue Selection Process from
      the perspective of goals and thought processes. Following IETF 94 and at
      IETF 95 there was a discussion on the IETF list of the selection process
      and criteria for IETF meetings. In response to that discussion, the IAOC
      and the IAOC Meetings Committee took it upon themselves to more publicly
      document its process and involve community input.</t>

      <t>This document describes the objectives and principles behind the
      venue selection process. It also discusses the actual selection process
      to one level of detail, and points to working documents used in
      execution.</t>

      <section anchor="language" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>Requirements called out in this document are identified as either
        "mandatory" or "desired", and considerations are tagged as "Important"
        or "Would be nice". For clarity, the terms are defined here: <list
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Mandatory:">If this requirement cannot be met, a
            location under consideration is unacceptable. We walk away.</t>

            <t hangText="Desired:">We would very much like to meet this
            requirement, but have frequently been unable to. The fact that we
            could not meet it is considered in comparison to other sites.</t>

            <t hangText="Important:">Can be a make-or-break consideration, but
            can also be traded off against other considerations.</t>

            <t hangText="Would be nice:">Not make-or-break, but warrants
            additional consideration if found to be true.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="objectives" title="Venue Selection Objectives">
      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Alissa's comment: "Why do we meet?," "Inclusiveness," and perhaps
          reformulated versions of some other items listed, per
          draft-sullivan-mtgvenue-decisions; 3.2)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The IETF, and therefore the IAOC and its Meetings Committee, have
      some core values that pervade the selection process. These are not
      limited to the following, but at minimum include them. <list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Why do we meet?"><vspace blankLines="0"/> We meet to
          advance Internet standards development, to advance Internet Drafts
          and RFCs. We meet to facilitate attendee participation in multiple
          topics and to enable cross-pollination of ideas and technology.</t>

          <t hangText="Inclusiveness:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>We would like
          to facilitate the onsite or remote participation of anyone who wants
          to be involved. Every country has limits on who it will permit
          within its borders. This principle of inclusiveness militates
          against the selection of venues within countries that impose visa
          regulations and/or laws that effectively exclude people on the basis
          of race, religion, gender, sexual orientation, or national origin,
          and to a lesser extent, reduces the likelihood of selecting
          countries that use such attributes to make entry difficult.</t>

          <t hangText="?">There may be other points from <xref
          target="principles-logic"/> to move here.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="nonobjectives" title="Venue Selection Non-Objectives">
      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.1 "Political considerations," 3.4)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>IETF meeting venues are not selected for the purposes of:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>endorsing or condemning particular countries, laws, regulations,
          policies, or policy positions.</t>

          <t>visiting new locations for the sake of variety in meeting
          locations.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="criteria" title="Venue Selection Criteria">
      <t>A number of criteria are considered during the site selection
      process. The list following is not sorted in any particular order, but
      includes the committee's major considerations.</t>

      <t>The selection of a venue always requires trade-offs. There are no
      perfect venues. For example, a site may not have a single hotel that can
      accommodate a significant number of the attendees of a typical IETF.
      That doesn't disqualify it, but it may reduce its desirability in the
      presence of an alternative that does.</t>

      <t>Each identified criterion is labeled with the terms defined above in
      <xref target="language"/>, i.e., "Mandatory", "Desired", "Important" or
      "Would be nice". These terms guide the trade-off analysis portion of the
      selection process. All "Mandatory" labeled criteria must be met for a
      venue to be selected. The remaining terms may be viewed as weighting
      factors.</t>

      <t>There are times where the evaluation of the criteria will be
      subjective. This is even the case for criteria labeled as "Mandatory".
      For this reason, the Meetings Committee will specifically review, and
      affirm to its satisfaction, that all "Mandatory" labeled criteria are
      satisfied by a particular venue and main IETF hotel as part of the
      process defined below in <xref target="phases"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="city" title="Venue City Criteria">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: 3.3.1 bullets 1, 5, 6, plus other bullets
            from <xref target="venueCisty_consideration-Old"/> if reformulated
            as criteria)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Note that these considerations are not "make or break" but flexible
        enough to allow for trade-offs and judgement on the part of the IAOC.
        Ideally, a city will meet all criteria. If all criteria cannot be met,
        the IETF community needs to consider the trade-off acceptable.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Travel to the venue is reasonably acceptable based on cost,
            time, and burden for participants traveling from multiple regions.
            It is anticipated that the burden borne will be generally shared
            over the course of the year. [Important]</t>

            <t>The venue is assessed as favorable for obtaining a host and
            sponsors. That is, the Meeting is in a location and at a price
            that it is possible and probable to find a host and sponsors.
            [Important]</t>

            <t>Ability to enter into a multi-event contract with the venue to
            optimize meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce
            administrative costs and reduce direct attendee costs, will be
            considered a positive factor. [Would be nice]</t>

            <t>Travel barriers to entry, e.g., visa requirements that can
            limit participation, are acceptable to the IETF community.
            [Important]</t>

            <t>Economic, safety, and health risks associated with this venue
            are acceptable to the IETF community. [Important]</t>

            <t>Available travel issue assessments (such as
            https://travel.state.gov/content/passports/en/country.html) have
            been pointed out the IETF community. [Important]</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="basic" title="Basic Venue Criteria">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.3.2 bullets 1, 3, 4, 5, 6)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The Meeting Space is adequate in size and layout to accommodate
            the meeting and foster participant interaction. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The cost of guest rooms, meeting space, meeting food and
            beverage is affordable (within the norms of business travel).
            [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The economics of the venue allow the meeting to be net cash
            positive [Mandatory].</t>

            <t>An Optimal Facility for an IETF meeting is held under "One
            Roof", that is, qualified meeting space and guest rooms are
            available in the same facility. [Desired]</t>

            <t>An Optimal Facility for an IETF meeting is accessible by people
            with disabilities. <list style="symbols">
                <t>The selected facility conforms with local accessibility
                laws and regulations [Mandatory]</t>

                <t>http://www.sigaccess.org/welcome-to-sigaccess/resources/accessible-conference-guide/
                provides a definition of related considerations that shall be
                used in evaluating this criterion. [Desired]</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="operations"
               title="Technical Services and Operations Criteria">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.3.3)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The Venue's support technologies and services -- network,
            audio- video, etc., are sufficient for the anticipated activities
            at the meeting, or the venue is willing to add such infrastructure
            at no or at an acceptable cost to the IETF. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The meeting venue must permit and facilitate the delivery of a
            high performance, robust, unfiltered and unmodified IETF Network.
            [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The IETF hotel(s), which are one or more hotels in close
            proximity to the venue where the primary IETF room allocations are
            negotiated and the IETF SSIDs are in use, must provide, or permit
            and facilitate, the delivery of a high performance, robust,
            unfiltered and unmodified Internet service for the public areas
            and guest rooms. This service is typically included in the cost of
            the room. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The overflow hotels should provide reasonable, reliable,
            unfiltered Internet service for the public areas and guest rooms.
            This service is typically included in the cost of the room.
            [Desired]</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="lodging" title="Lodging Criteria">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.3.4)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The IETF hotel(s) are within close proximity to each other and
            the venue. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The Guest Rooms at the IETF hotel(s) are sufficient in number
            to house 1/3 or more of projected meeting attendees.
            [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The Venue environs include budget hotels within convenient
            travel time, cost, and effort. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>Overflow Hotels that can be placed under contract. They
            typically must be within convenient travel time of the venue and
            have a variety of guest room rates. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The IETF hotel(s) are accessible by people with disabilities.
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>The selected facility conforms with local accessibility
                laws and regulations [Mandatory]</t>

                <t>http://www.sigaccess.org/welcome-to-sigaccess/resources/accessible-conference-guide/
                provides a definition of related considerations that shall be
                used in evaluating this criterion. [Desired]</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="food" title="Food and Beverage Criteria">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.3.5)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The Venue environs, which includes onsite, and the areas within
            a reasonable walking distance, or conveniently accessible by a
            short taxi, bus, or subway ride, has convenient and inexpensive
            choices for meals that can accommodate a wide range of dietary
            requirements. [Mandatory]</t>

            <t>The Venue environs include grocery shopping that will
            accommodate a wide range of dietary requirements, within a
            reasonable walking distance, or conveniently accessible by a short
            taxi, bus, or subway ride. [Desired]</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="process" title="Venue Selection Process">
      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Alissa's comment: ( 2)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The formal structure of IETF administrative support functions is
      documented in <xref target="RFC4071">BCP 101</xref><xref
      target="RFC4371"/><xref target="RFC7691"/>. The reader is expected to be
      familiar with the entities and roles defined by that document, in
      particular for the IASA, ISOC, IAOC and IAD. This section covers the
      meeting selection related roles of these and other parties that
      participate in the process. Note that roles beyond meeting selection,
      e.g., actually running and reporting on meetings, are outside the scope
      of this document.</t>

      <section title="The IETF Community">
        <t>While somewhat obvious to most, it is important to note that IETF
        meetings serve all those who contribute to the development of IETF
        RFCs. This includes those who attend meetings, from newcomer to
        frequent attendee, to those who participate remotely, and to those who
        don't attend but contribute to new RFCs. Potential new contributors
        are also considered in the process.</t>

        <t>IETF consensus with respect to the meeting venue selection process
        is judged via standard IETF process and not by any other means, e.g.,
        surveys. Surveys are used to gather information related to meeting
        venues, but not to measure consensus.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IESG and IETF Chair">
        <t>The Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) is a group comprised
        of the IETF Area Directors and the IETF Chair. The IESG is responsible
        for the management, along with the IAB, of the IETF, and is the
        standards approval board for the IETF, as described in <xref
        target="RFC2026">BCP9</xref>. This means that the IESG sets high level
        policies related to, among other things, meeting venues. The IETF
        Chair is a member of the IESG who, among other things, relays policies
        to the IAOC. The IETF Chair is also a member of the IAOC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Internet Society">
        <t>The Internet Society (ISOC) executes all venue contracts on behalf
        of the IETF at the request of the IAOC; solicits meeting sponsorships;
        collects all meeting-related revenues, including registration fees,
        sponsorships, hotel commissions, and other miscellaneous revenues.
        ISOC also provides accounting services, such as invoicing and monthly
        financial statements. The meetings budget is managed by the IAD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Oversight Committee">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) has the
        responsibility to oversee and select IETF meeting venues. It instructs
        the IAD to work with the Internet Society to write the relevant
        contracts. It approves the IETF meetings calendar.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Support Activity">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA) supports the
        meeting selection process. This includes identifying, qualifying and
        reporting on potential meeting sites, as well as supporting meeting
        venue contract negotiation. The IETF Secretariat is part of the IASA
        under the management of the IAD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Director">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Director (IAD) coordinates and supports the
        activities of the IETF Secretariat, the IAOC Meetings Committee and
        the IAOC to ensure the timely execution of the meeting process. This
        includes participating in the IAOC Meeting Subcommittee and ensuring
        its efforts are documented, leading venue contract negotiation, and
        coordinating contract execution with ISOC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IAOC Meeting Committee">
        <t>The IAOC Meeting Committee is generally referred to as the Meetings
        Committee.</t>

        <t>The fundamental purpose of the committee is to participate in the
        venue selection process, and to formulate recommendations to the IAOC
        regarding meeting sites. It also tracks the meetings sponsorship
        program, recommends extraordinary meeting-related expenses, and
        recommends the IETF meetings calendar to the IAOC. The charter of the
        committee is located here:
        https://iaoc.ietf.org/committees.html#meetings.</t>

        <t>Membership in the Meetings Committee is at the discretion of the
        IAOC; it includes an IAOC appointed chair, the IETF Administrative
        Director (IAD), IAOC members, representatives from the Secretariat,
        and interested members of the community.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="phases" title="Venue Selection Phases">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Alissa's comment: ( 3.5, perhaps with additional detail
            currently in 3.3.1 bullets 2, 3, 4)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Commencing the process four years in advance of an event results in
        the following schedule as a guideline:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Phase 1:">Identification and Preliminary
            Investigation <vspace blankLines="0"/>Four years out, a process
            identifies cities for meetings and initiates site selection. <list
                style="letters">
                <t>The IAOC selects regions for meetings.</t>

                <t>Meeting target cities per region are provided to the
                Secretariat based upon Meetings Committee input and, if known,
                host preferences.</t>

                <t>Potential venues in preferred cities identified and
                investigated, including reviews of Official Advisory Sources,
                consultation with specialty travel services, frequent
                travelers and local contacts to identify possible barriers to
                holding a successful meeting in the target cities.</t>

                <t>Investigated cities and findings are provided by the
                Secretariat to the Meetings Committee for review. Meetings
                Committee makes a recommendation to the IAOC of
                investigated/target cities to consider further as well as
                issues identified and the results of research conducted.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="Phase 2:">Community Consultation <vspace
            blankLines="0"/>The IAOC asks the community whether there are any
            barriers to holding a successful meeting in the target cities.
            Community responses are reviewed and concerns investigated. IAOC
            provides a list of vetted cities to the Meetings Committee to
            pursue as potential meeting locations.</t>

            <t hangText="Phase 3:">Vetted Venues Evaluated for Site
            Qualification Visit <list style="letters">
                <t>Secretariat Assesses "vetted" target cities to determine
                availability and conformance to criteria</t>

                <t>Meetings Committee approves potential cities for site
                qualification visit.</t>

                <t>Site qualification visits are arranged by Secretariat and
                preliminary negotiations are undertaken with selected
                potential sites</t>

                <t>Site qualification visit is conducted using the checklist
                from
                https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html;
                The site visit team prepares a site report and discusses it
                with the Meetings Committee.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="Phase 4:">Qualified Venues Evaluated for Contract
            <vspace blankLines="0"/>2.75 - 3 years out, initiate contract
            negotiations. <list style="letters">
                <t>The Meetings Committee reviews the venue options based on
                venue selection criteria and recommends a venue to the IAOC.
                Only options that meet all Mandatory labeled criteria may be
                recommended.</t>

                <t>IAOC selects a venue for contracting as well as a back-up
                contracting venue, if available.</t>

                <t>Secretariat negotiates with selected venue. IAD reviews
                contract and requests IAOC and ISOC approval of contract and
                authority for Secretariat to execute contract on ISOC's
                behalf.</t>

                <t>Contracts are executed.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="Phase 5:">Evaluation and Contingency Planning <vspace
            blankLines="0"/>3 Months Prior to the Meeting, the meeting site is
            checked for continued availability and conformance to
            expectations. <list style="letters">
                <t>Secretariat reviews current status of the contracted
                meeting location to confirm there is no change in the location
                status and to identify possible new barriers to holding a
                successful meeting in the contracted city and provides
                findings to the IAOC.</t>

                <t>IAOC considers the information provided and evaluates the
                risk - if significant risk is identified, the Contingency
                Planning Flow Chart
                (https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html)
                is followed, if current risk is not significant, the situation
                is monitored through the meeting to ensure there is no
                significant change.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Text carried forward">
      <t>This document is being reorganized along an outline proposed by
      Alissa Cooper. In preceding sections, her comment is made explicit. That
      is intended to be removed when the reorganization is complete. Text in
      this section is left over and will potentially be moved to preceding
      sections.</t>

      <section anchor="principles-old" title="Venue Selection Process">
        <t>The process of selecting a venue is described below and is based on
        https://iaoc.ietf.org/venue-selection.html.</t>

        <section anchor="principles-logic" title="Venue Selection Principles">
          <t>heading paragraph moved to <xref target="objectives"/>. <list
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Who are we?"><vspace blankLines="0"/> We are
              computer scientists, engineers, network operators, academics,
              and other interested parties sharing the goal of making the
              Internet work better. At this time, the vast majority of
              attendees come from North America, Western and Central Europe,
              and Eastern Asia. We also have participants from other
              regions.</t>

              <t hangText="Why do we meet?">Moved to <xref
              target="objectives"/>.</t>

              <t hangText="Where do we meet?"><vspace blankLines="0"/> We meet
              in different locations globally in order to spread the pain and
              cost of travel among active participants, balancing travel time
              and expense across the regions from where IETF participants are
              based. We also aim to enhance inclusiveness and new
              contributions.</t>

              <t hangText="Inclusiveness:">Moved to <xref
              target="objectives"/>.</t>

              <t hangText="Internet Access:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As an
              organization, we write specifications for the Internet, and we
              use it heavily. Meeting attendees need unfiltered access to the
              general Internet and our corporate networks, which are usually
              reached using encrypted VPNs from the meeting venue and hotels,
              including overflow hotels. We also need open network access
              available at high enough data rates to support our work,
              including the support of remote participation.</t>

              <t hangText="Focus:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>We meet to have
              focused technical discussions. These are not limited to breakout
              sessions, although of course those are important; they also
              happen over meals or drinks (including a specific type of
              non-session that we call a "Bar BOF"), or in side meetings.
              Environments that are noisy or distracting prevent that or
              reduce its effectiveness, and are therefore less desirable as a
              meeting venue.</t>

              <t hangText="Economics:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Meeting
              attendees participate as individuals. While many have their
              participation underwritten by employers or sponsors, there are
              many who do not. Locations that do not provide convenient budget
              alternatives for food and lodging, or which are multiple travel
              segments from major airports, are therefore exclusionary, and
              violate our value of "Inclusiveness". Within reason, budget
              should not be a barrier to accommodation.</t>

              <t hangText="Political considerations:">moved to <xref
              target="nonobjectives"/> and reworded per Alissa's suggested
              text.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Objectives">
          <t>Venues for meetings are selected to advance the objectives of the
          IETF, which are discussed in
          https://www.ietf.org/about/mission.html. The IAOC's supporting
          objectives include: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Advancing standards development</t>

              <t>Facilitating participation by active contributors</t>

              <t>Sharing the travel pain; balancing travel time and expense
              across the regions from where IETF participants are based.</t>

              <t>Encouraging new contributors</t>

              <t>Generating funds to support IETF operations in support of
              standards development, including the Secretariat, IASA, and the
              RFC Editor.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>There is an explicit intent to rotate meeting locations equally
          among several places in accordance with IETF policy. However, a
          consistent balance is sometimes difficult to achieve. The IAOC has
          an objective of setting the Regions 4 years in advance, meeting in
          Europe, North America, and Asia, with a possibility of occasionally
          meeting outside those regions. This policy, known as the 1-1-1*
          model, is set by the IESG,
          https://iaoc.ietf.org/minutes/2010-11-10-iaoc-minutes.txt, and is
          further discussed in <xref
          target="I-D.krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy"/>. The reason for the
          multi-year timeframe is maximization of opportunities; the smaller
          the time available to qualify and contract a conference venue, the
          more stress imposed on the qualification process, and the greater
          the risk of not finding a suitable venue or paying more for it.</t>

          <t>There is no formal policy regarding rotation of regions, the time
          of year for a meeting in a specific region, or whether a meeting in
          a non-targeted region replaces a visit to one of the regions during
          that year.</t>

          <t>The IETF chair drives selection of "*" locations, i.e., venues
          outside the usual regions, and requires community input. These
          selections usually arise from evidence of growing interest and
          participation in the new region. Expressions of interest from
          possible hosts also factor into the meeting site selection process,
          for any meeting.</t>

          <t>Increased participation in the IETF from those other regions,
          electronically or in person, could result in basic changes to the
          overall pattern, and we encourage those who would like for that to
          occur to encourage participation from those regions.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Criteria">
          <t>Heading text moved to <xref target="criteria"/>.</t>

          <section anchor="venueCisty_consideration-Old"
                   title="Venue City Considerations">
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Consideration will be given to whether it makes sense to
                enter into a multi-event contract with the venue to optimize
                meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce administrative
                costs and reduce direct attendee costs. [Would be nice]</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Basic Venue Criteria">
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>moved to <xref target="basic"/></t>

                <t>The venue and hotels can be put under contract. The
                subsequent failure to put a selected venue under contract will
                result in a re-evaluation of the venues and selection for the
                meeting. [Mandatory]</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Phases"/>

        <section title="Experience Notes">
          <t><list style="letters">
              <t>The foregoing process works with reasonable certainty in
              North America and Europe.</t>

              <t>Experience to date for Asia and Latin America is that
              contracts take longer and often will not be executed more than
              two years in advance of the meeting. While the IETF will have
              the first option for the dates, for reasons not completely
              understood contracts won't be executed.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Transparency">
        <t>BCP 101 requires transparency in IASA process and contracts, and
        thereby of the meetings committee. BCP 101 also states that the IAOC
        approves what information is to remain confidential. Therefore any
        information produced by the meetings committee or related to meetings
        that individuals believe is confidential, e.g., venue contracts, must
        be confirmed to be confidential by the IAOC.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo asks the IANA for no new parameters.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This note proposes no protocols, and therefore no new protocol
      insecurities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This note reveals no personally identifying information apart from
      its authorship.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Additional commentary came from Jari Arkko, Scott Bradner, and Alissa
      Cooper. It was discussed on mtgvenue@ietf.org.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- references split to informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2026" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4071" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4371" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7691" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.barnes-healthy-food" ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="log" title="Change Log">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="2016-01-12:">Initial version</t>

          <t hangText="2016-01-21:">Update to reflect
          https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionCriteriaJan2016.pdf
          and
          https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionProcess11Jan16.pdf,
          accessed from
          https://iaoc.ietf.org/private/privatemeetings.html.</t>

          <t hangText="2016-02-23:">Reorganize and capture IAOC Meetings
          Committee discussions.</t>

          <t hangText="2016-03-03:">Final from Design Team.</t>

          <t hangText="2016-03-17:">First update incorporating
          mtgvenue@ietf.org comments</t>

          <t hangText="2016-05-20">Updated in accordance with editing by Laura
          Nugent, Dave Crocker, Lou Berger, Fred Baker, and others.</t>

          <t hangText="posting as working group draft">August 2, 2016</t>

          <t hangText="Reorganized per Alissa Cooper outline">Work in
          progress. In addition, contributors were re-organized to be
          authors.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
